{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This deity wore an Atef crown decorated with ostrich feathers, and was fused with Apis to become Serapis in the Hellenic period. This “foremost westerner’s” spine was represented by djed pillars after he was found in a lead-sealed box at Byblos by his wife, who retrieved this god’s body after he was tricked by his brother, Set. For ten points, name this husband of Isis and father of Horus, the Egyptian god of the dead.",
      "answer": "Osiris or Asir"
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader thanked “the grace of Ahura Mazda” on the Behistun inscription. He ordered his lands into 20 satrapies, and this son of Cambyses II [cam-BYE-sees] built the Apadana at the ceremonial city of Persepolis. The Ionian Revolt targeted this ruler; in revenge, he launched an invasion that was stymied in 490 BC. For ten points, name this Persian emperor whose army was turned back at Marathon.",
      "answer": [
        "Darius I",
        "Darius the Great"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "With David Scott, this man docked with an Agena vehicle, making Gemini 8 the first docking of two orbiting spacecraft. This man, a retired U.S. Navy pilot upon becoming an astronaut, died in 2012. As the Command Module Columbia was piloted by Michael Collins, this man flew with Buzz Aldrin and took “one small step for a man”. For ten points, name this commander of the Apollo 11 mission, the first man to walk on the Moon.",
      "answer": "Neil Armstrong"
    },
    {
      "question": "This author created analogies of the divided line and the Sun in a work featuring his brothers, Adeimantus and Glaucon. This man, who was briefly sold into slavery on Syracuse, developed a theory of eternal forms and compared the city to the soul in a work that advocated rule by philosopher-kings. For ten points, name this Greek philosopher who recorded his teacher, Socrates, in dialogues like The Apology and wrote The Republic.",
      "answer": "Plato"
    },
    {
      "question": "Thomas Henry Burge and Lord Frederick Cavendish were murdered in Phoenix Park in this city, and this city is home to a war memorial known as the Garden of Remembrance located on Parnell Square. It served as the capital of a free state until a 1937 constitution. The assassinations of the Cairo gang, a group of British intelligence officers, by the IRA sparked Bloody Sunday in this city. For ten points, name this capital of Ireland.",
      "answer": "Dublin"
    },
    {
      "question": "One of these compositions uses words by August Hoffmann and includes a second movement dedicated to wine, women, and song. One of these pieces shares a melody with The Moldau movement of Smetana’s Ma Vlast. Another of these pieces uses the melody “To Anacreon in Heaven” as the setting for a poem commemorating Fort McHenry’s bombardment in the War of 1812 written by Francis Scott Key. For ten points, the Hatikvah, “Deutchlandlied” and “The Star-Spangled Banner” are all what type of song, which is used to represent its country?",
      "answer": "national anthems"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Dutch built Fort Provintia on this island; today, Chihkan Tower stands at the former fort in the city of Tainan, which was this island’s capital during the Qing [CHING] dynasty. This island, once known as Formosa, was the destination of Chiang Kai-shek’s retreating Kuomintang. For ten points, name this island off the southeast coast of China, which disputes its sovereignty.",
      "answer": [
        "Taiwan or Republic of China",
        "Zhonghua Minguo",
        "Formosa before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Amos Akerman and Benjamin Bristow were appointed by this President as part of the Department of Justice, which this man created. This man put down the 1874 Brooks-Baxter War between two factions of the Republican Party. The Force Acts were passed by this President to safeguard African-Americans’ right to vote, and the end of his term marked the end of the Reconstruction Era. For ten points, name this U.S. President, a former general nicknamed “Unconditional Surrender” for his role in the U.S. Civil War.",
      "answer": "Ulysses S. Grant"
    },
    {
      "question": "The election of Stephen Langton to one post led to the signing of this document, which was supported by the Charter of the Forest. One clause from this document formed a council of 25 nobles to ensure its enforcement while another dealt with the removal of fish weirs. This document was proposed after a ruler lost the Battle of Bouvines and signed at Runnymede. For ten points, name this 1215 document signed by King John of England which granted rights to barons.",
      "answer": "Magna Carta"
    },
    {
      "question": "The last U.S. battleship to be completed was named for this state and christened by Margaret, the daughter of a then-Senator from this state. That battleship, now a museum next to the USS Arizona memorial, sailed to Tokyo for the signing of the Japanese surrender ending World War II. For ten points, name this U.S. state where Harry Truman lived in Independence, just outside Kansas City.",
      "answer": [
        "Missouri",
        "USS Missouri"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The leader who sent this force quipped that “He sent [this] against men, not God’s wind and waves”. This entity, which was directed by the Duke of Medina Sidonia, fared poorly against “Hell burners”, and was defeated at the Battle of Gravelines. This entity’s failure was attributed to the “Protestant Wind”, and it was sent to force one country to stop supporting Dutch rebels in the Eighty Years War. For ten points, name this massive naval fleet commanded by Phillip II whose goal was to invade England.",
        "answer": "Spanish Armada"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This monarch, who gave the “Tilbury” speech to her troops, was the target of the Spanish Armada and the daughter of Henry VIII and Anne Boleyn",
        "answer": "Elizabeth I"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During Japanese occupation of this city, its Chinese inhabitants were targeted by the Sook Ching massacre. After pleading guilty to vandalizing cars, American teenager Michael P. Fay was sentenced to caning in this city. It was nicknamed the “Gibraltar of the East” under British rule, which had begun under the leadership of Stamford Raffles. Lee Kwan Yew was the “Father” of, for ten points, what Southeast Asian city-state?",
        "answer": "Republic of Singapore"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Singapore was part of this Southeast Asian nation for two years, until it expelled Singapore in 1965.",
        "answer": "Malaysia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "H.L. Barnum argued that this author’s character Harvey Birch, the protagonist of The Spy, was based on the American Revolution soldier Enoch Crosby. This man’s best known work is a fictionalization of the defense of Fort William Henry during the French and Indian War and features Chingachgook as the title character. For ten points, name this author of The Leatherstocking Tales, the most famous of which was The Last of the Mohicans.",
        "answer": "James Fenimore Cooper"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This author of The Literary Offenses of James Fenimore Cooper set his novel The Prince and the Pauper in 16th century England.",
        "answer": [
          "Mark Twain",
          "Samuel Langhorne Clemens"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The first prototype of these objects was constructed by William Foster & Co., and nicknamed Little Willie. Modified versions of these objects, including Crocodiles and Crabs, carried flails and laid bridges and were named Hobart’s Funnies. The Landship Commission developed the Mark line of these objects, which were first used in the Battle of Cambrai. Developed in response to stagnant trench warfare in WWI, for ten points, what vehicles, such as the M4 Sherman, use tracks instead of wheels and have a lot of armor?",
        "answer": [
          "Tanks",
          "landships before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Hobart’s Funnies were, like Mulberry harbors, designed after the failed Dieppe Raid to meet the challenges of this 1944 invasion in Northern France.",
        "answer": "Invasion of Normandy"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A hill creatively named Cornhill provided much of the early food for this colony, which was founded near Cole’s Hill. Josiah Cotton served as this colony’s Register of Deeds for some time. Its militia was run by Miles Standish, and William Bradford served as governor for this colony. For ten points, what early colony was founded by Pilgrims attempting to find Virginia by sailing on the Mayflower?",
        "answer": "Plymouth Colony"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Samoset and this other English-speaking Native American from the Wampanoag tribe helped the first Pilgrims survive the winter, an event commemorated as the First Thanksgiving.",
        "answer": "Squanto"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Minnesota case of Baker v. Nelson upheld a statute forbidding this action. The 12th anniversary of Lawrence v. Texas coincided with the decision in a Supreme Court case that legalized this practice. U.S. v. Windsor struck down Section 3 of DOMA, which allowed states to reject these events until 2013. For ten points, name this social right made legal in all 50 states by 2015’s Obergefell v Hodges.",
        "answer": [
          "same-sex marriage or gay marriage",
          "descriptive answers"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Kim Davis, a clerk from this state, refused to issue marriage licenses after the Obergefell decision due to personal beliefs.",
        "answer": "Kentucky"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This city sought to demolish the Western Metal Supply Company building, then decided to use it for the left field foul pole in a baseball stadium. This city’s Major League Baseball team lost the 1984 and 1998 World Series, despite the hitting of Tony Gwynn, and its NFL team, led by Philip Rivers, is considering leaving Qualcomm Stadium for Los Angeles in 2016. For ten points, name this Southern California city home to baseball’s Padres and, for possibly not much longer, football’s Chargers.",
        "answer": "San Diego"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This other NFL team, once owned by the late Al Davis, is considering moving back to Los Angeles after two decades and numerous NFL lawsuits in the Bay Area.",
        "answer": [
          "Oakland Raiders",
          "either city",
          "team name"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Catonsville Nine were Catholic activists who protested this war. The case Tinker v. Des Moines protected students’ rights to protest against this war in schools. Napalm was heavily used in aerial offensives during this war, which saw large use of Agent Orange to destroy foliage. For ten points, name this Southeast Asian war won in 1975 by a Communist country once led by Ho Chi Minh.",
        "answer": "Vietnam War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "”Big-belly” modifications to these American bombers during the Vietnam War allowed them to perform carpet bombings.",
        "answer": [
          "Boeing B-52 Stratofortress",
          "either"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Baseball",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "home city of the Negro Leagues’ Monarchs and the 2015 World Series champion Royals.",
          "answer": "Kansas City"
        },
        {
          "question": "team whose “Core Four,” including Mariano Rivera and Derek Jeter, won five World Series.",
          "answer": "New York Yankees"
        },
        {
          "question": "MLB team that signed Jackie Robinson to break the color barrier.",
          "answer": [
            "Brooklyn Dodgers",
            "city",
            "team name"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "St. Louis Cardinal slugger whose 70 home runs in 1998 won a “race” with Sammy Sosa.",
          "answer": "Mark McGwire"
        },
        {
          "question": "event, called the “Midsummer Classic,” where teams ran out of players in 2002, causing a controversial tie game.",
          "answer": "All-Star Game"
        },
        {
          "question": "team once owned by Nazi-sympathizer Marge Schott, which won two World Series with Pete Rose?",
          "answer": [
            "Cincinnati Reds",
            "city",
            "team name"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "controversial event that prematurely ended the 1994 season and canceled the World Series?",
          "answer": "players’ strike"
        },
        {
          "question": "Chicago Cubs executive who ended the “Curse of the Bambino” as Boston’s General Manager in 2004?",
          "answer": [
            "Theo Epstein The Light Has Gone Out The phrase “the light has gone out of my life,”",
            "“of our lives,” has been used momentously twice in"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "history. Name the...",
      "prompt": "Name the history. name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "U.S. President and Rough Rider who wrote that phrase in his diary in 1884.",
          "answer": "Theodore “Teddy” Roosevelt"
        },
        {
          "question": "Only other letter used by Roosevelt in that diary entry.",
          "answer": "X"
        },
        {
          "question": "Non-violent Indian independence leader who was assassinated in 1948.",
          "answer": "Mohandas or Mahatma Gandhi"
        },
        {
          "question": "City in which that assassination took place, the capital of India.",
          "answer": "New Delhi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Indian Prime Minister whose speech to the country after that assassination used the phrase.",
          "answer": "Jawaharlal Nehru"
        },
        {
          "question": "Latin-derived term that describes that speech, as it was delivered with no preparation.",
          "answer": [
            "extemperaneous or word forms",
            "ex tempore",
            "impromptu"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Hindu nationalist who carried out the assassination in India.",
          "answer": "Nathuram Vinayak Godse"
        },
        {
          "question": "British Earl, later killed in his fishing boat by the IRA, who encouraged the Prime Minister to give the speech.",
          "answer": "Louis Mountbatten, 1st Earl Mountbatten of Burma"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Islands",
      "prompt": "Which island...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "is a former Danish colony and - not counting Australia - the world’s largest?",
          "answer": "Greenland"
        },
        {
          "question": "has been ruled by either Fidel or Raul Castro since its 1959 revolution?",
          "answer": "Cuba"
        },
        {
          "question": "is the world’s second largest, and is home to the Indonesian province of Papua and a former Australian colony?",
          "answer": "New Guinea"
        },
        {
          "question": "is shared by the Dominican Republic and Haiti and is where Columbus lost the Santa Maria?",
          "answer": "Hispaniola"
        },
        {
          "question": "lost its Minoan civilization after a volcanic eruption on Thera?",
          "answer": "Crete"
        },
        {
          "question": "is the northernmost of Japan’s four main islands and home to many indigenous Ainu people in Hidaku?",
          "answer": "Hokkaido"
        },
        {
          "question": "was the site of the Great Kanto Earthquake of 1923?",
          "answer": "Honshu"
        },
        {
          "question": "was flown over by Korean Air 007, which was then shot down by Soviets in 1983?",
          "answer": "Sakhalin"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Roswell Field took over a pro bono defense for this case after the death of David Hall. Benjamin Curtis and John McLean dissented in this case, which concerned the defendant’s time spent in (20 pts)",
        "Wisconsin. Roger Taney’s [TAW-nee’s] decision in this case was a dismissal on grounds that the defendant could not legally (10 pts)",
        "file a lawsuit. The Missouri Compromise was ruled unconstitutional by, for ten points, what 1857 Supreme Court case that ruled African-Americans were not U.S. citizens?"
      ],
      "answer": "Dred Scott v. James F. A. Sanford or Dred Scott v. Sandford"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man heavily weakened the influence of John Lilburne’s Leveller Faction, against whom he and his son-in-law Henry Ireton argued in the Putney Debates. He rose to power with John Lambert’s Instrument of Government and increased his influence by ordering (20 pts)",
        "Pride’s Purge, which ended the Long Parliament and instituted the Rump Parliament. This man’s victory at the Battle of Preston during a war that saw his service in the (10 pts)",
        "New Model Army under Thomas Fairfax led to the execution of the Stuart king Charles I. For ten points, name this “Lord Protector,” who won the English Civil War."
      ],
      "answer": "Oliver Cromwell"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In 2008, 300,000 people in this country were injured when melamine was added to food, particularly infant formula. In 2010, the US Embassy in this country’s capital tweeted that its AQI reached 700, briefly calling it “crazy bad.” The 2002-03 (20 pts)",
        "SARS outbreak began in this country, where almost 70,000 people were killed by the 2008 (10 pts)",
        "Sichaun earthquake. For ten points, name this country where factories were shut down to clear the air prior to the 2008 Summer Olympics in Beijing."
      ],
      "answer": "People’s Republic of China"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This musician canceled a tour of the USSR and said Eisenhower had “no guts” in response to the President’s reluctance to intervene on behalf of the Little Rock Nine. According to legend, he dropped his sheet music while recording (20 pts)",
        "“Heebie Jeebies;” his improvised wordless vocals popularized scat singing. This leader of the (10 pts)",
        "Hot Five earned a number one hit at the age of 63 with his cover of “Hello Dolly”. For ten points, name this jazz trumpeter and vocalist, nicknamed “Satchmo,” who also sang “What a Wonderful World.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Louis Armstrong"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This editor of the Avanti! newspaper threatened to invade Greece in the Corfu Affair and saw members of Parliament leave after supporters of his party killed Giacomo (20 pts)",
        "Matteotti. This leader allied with Adolf Hitler by signing the Pact of Steel, 17 years after forcing Victor (10 pts)",
        "Emmanuel III to name him as Prime Minister after leading the Blackshirts in a March on Rome. For ten points, name this Fascist Italian Prime Minister during World War II."
      ],
      "answer": "Benito Mussolini"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The world’s largest rubber plantation is in this country’s city of Harbel. Samuel Doe was overthrown and executed by the rebel group National Patriotic Front, led by Charles (20 pts)",
        "Taylor. The American Colonization Society founded this country as a home for freed slaves; with Ethiopia, it was one of two (10 pts)",
        "African countries never to be colonized by European powers. For ten points, name this African country that honored a U.S. President with the name of its capital, Monrovia."
      ],
      "answer": "Liberia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Antonio Canova sculpted this man as Mars the Peacemaker, and he was painted by Antoine-Jean Gros Visiting the Plague Victims of Jaffa. This man’s military accomplishments are celebrated with the (20 pts)",
        "Vendome Column, and in an Ingres [ANG-gruh] painting that shows this man wearing a gold wreath and holding the scepter of Charlemagne while seated on his (10 pts)",
        "Imperial Throne. A painting of this man by Jacques-Louis David shows him perched on a rearing horse while Crossing the Alps. For ten points, name this French emperor who was defeated at Waterloo."
      ],
      "answer": "Napoleon Bonaparte or Napoleon I"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Security guard Frank Wills uncovered the central incident in this event, which led to the second use of 96-point font in New York Times history, after the Moon landings. It was masterminded by G. Gordon (20 pts)",
        "Liddy and E. Howard Hunt. This event was investigated by (10 pts)",
        "Washington Post reporters Carl Bernstein and Bob Woodward, who received tips from an informant known as “Deep Throat.” The burglary of the DNC headquarters and ensuing coverup were the subject of, for ten points, what scandal that resulted in the resignation of Richard Nixon."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Watergate scandal",
        "descriptions of Nixon’s resignation before mentioned"
      ]
    }
  ]
}